Guide to the William Harlan Hale Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
William Harlan Hale papers
1915-1970
MS 1140
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
9
(22 boxes, 1 folio)
Correspondence, writings, memoranda, reports, printed matter, and memorabilia, chiefly documenting Hale's career as a journalist, as a member of intelligence units in the United States Army during and after World War II, and later as a member of the foreign service in Austria (1950-1953). His correspondence is largely with editors, publishers, and writers about the projected articles, or about the magazines that he sucessively edited, especially the New Republic, the Reporter, and Horizon. Prominent correspondents are Max Ascoli, founder of the Reporter, Bruce Bliven, and Oswald Garrison Villard. During World War II and just after the end of the war, when Hale was on the staff of the Psychological Warfare Branch of the Allied Expeditionary Force, he collected numerous memoranda analyzing German public opinion, including both civilians and German prisoners of war. Also included are reports on visits to Buchenwald (1945 Apr 12) and Dachau (1945 May 24) immediately after the camps were freed. The collection contains more than one hundred leaflets illustrating the psychological warfare conducted by the Allies during the war, and printed propaganda issued by the Germans, the British, and the Americans as well. His service in Vienna is documented by a diary (1951-1952), State Department memoranda, and extensive anti-Soviet printed matter issued by the United States at the height of the Cold War.
Hale, William Harlan, 1910-1974
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. William H. Hale, 1975.
Arrangement
Arranged in five series: I. Correspondence. II. Writings. III. Personal and Biographical Papers. IV. Topical Files. V. Printed Matter.
Scope and Contents
The papers of William Harlan Hale, who was a prolific writer and editor, reflect the intellectual and political climate of Yale (1928-1931); the publishing world of New York in the 1930s; the atmosphere of the intelligence branches of the Allied forces during World War II in New York, London, and Germany; and the politics of the Cold War as seen from Europe in the 1950s when Hale was in Vienna attached to the American embassy. The material, which is particularly voluminous for the 1940s and 1950s, has been arranged in five series: I. Correspondence, II. Writings, III. Personal and Biographical Papers IV. Topical Files, V. Printed Matter.
Series I is divided into general and select correspondence. The General Correspondence, which makes up the larger portion of the series, is almost entirely professional, and largely correspondence with editors, publishers and writers about projected articles or about the various publications with which Hale was connected. Two such letters are those from Oswald Garrison Villard (1932 Dec 27) and Bruce Bliven (1941 Aug 7). In response to an article that Hale had written on architecture, Richard Neutra, the Austrian-born architect, wrote a four-page letter (1935 Jul 4) giving a detailed history of his arrival and subsequent career in the United States. The magazines with which Hale was connected and which figure most prominently in the correspondence are: American Heritage, Harpers, Horizon, the Nation, the New Republic and the Harkness Hoot. In 1930, as Yale undergraduates, Hale and Selden Rodman had been co-founders of this publication. The General Correspondence is arranged chronologically. The smaller section, Select Correspondence, is made up of correspondence with several persons with whom Hale had a substantial exchange, and a few family letters. Included here are a series of internal office memoranda, both to and from Hale while on the Reporter magazine (1954-1958); also copies of five letters to Hale from prominent persons which were sold by Hale in 1970. The writers are Robinson Jeffers, H. L. Mencken, Katherine Anne Porter, Thorton Wilder, and Frank Lloyd Wright.
Series II is made up of manuscript drafts of many articles (1919-1970) and partial and complete drafts of books with related correspondence, research notes, reviews, etc. Also in this series are the texts of his broadcasts to Europe written for the Office of War Information (1942 Nov 9 - 1944 Jan 20).
In Series III, PERSONAL AND BIOGRAPHICAL PAPERS, are school and travel memorabilia, clippings, photographs, and a typescript diary kept by Hale (1951-1952) while he was in Austria as director of United States Public Affairs. A collection of books by Selden Rodman with flyleaf inscriptions to William Harlan Hale completes this series.
Series IV, TOPICAL FILES, contains important typescript and mimeographed materials collected (or written) by Hale while in Germany with the Psychological Warfare Branch of the Allied Expeditionary Force (1941-1945) and later as an officer in military intelligence (1948-1949). Taken together these documents reveal the psychological state and political ideas of German civilians and soldiers from the first day of American occupation. Many contain records of interviews, or analyze the results of questionnaires distributed among the general population. Of special interest are two reports on Buchenwald and Dachau, made on April 24 and May 12, 1945, respectively, depicting the situation in these camps almost from the moment of liberation. Included in this series are also transcripts of German broadcasts (1943 Feb 28-Jun 16) and Hale's notes and memoranda on the State Department (1955-1956).
Series V, PRINTED MATTER, has leaflets, periodicals, and books, dating chiefly from World War II, and arranged by issuing agency or country. It includes leaflets and newspapers issued by the Psychological Warfare Branch as part of its propaganda campaign during the war, campaign histories for both the European and Pacific theaters issued by the United States government (1944-1946), British publications, and a number of pieces of Nazi war propaganda as well as Nazi literature intended for home consumption. A rare item in this section is an early publication of the Nazi party, Deutschlands Erwachen, with photographs by Hans Hoffmann (ca. 1924). Collected by Hale during the 1950s are also some telling examples of anti-Soviet literature, largely in German, issued by the United States. A European view of this period is represented in the collection by several pieces of anti-American literature, mostly of French origin.
The papers were the gift of Mrs. William Harlan Hale in July and August 1975. For additional family papers, see the papers of William Bayard Hale (MS 814), father of William Harlan Hale. For related papers dealing with World War II, see the German Pamphlet Collection (MS 735), the World War II Collection (MS 671), the Historical Picture Collection (MS 713), and the Barbara Tuchman Papers (MS 574) for materials on the Burma campaign. For the papers of other journalists of the period, see the Hanson Baldwin Papers (MS 54), the Max Lerner Papers (MS 322), the Walter Lippmann Papers (MS 326), and the Dwight Macdonald Papers (MS 730).
Biographical / Historical
Born 1910, New York City, son of William Bayard and Olga Unger Hale. Educated at Riverdale Country School and schools abroad; B.A. Yale University 1931. Married Jean Laughlin Barker of Santa Fe, New Mexico, 1931; children: Katherine Laughlin, Jonathan Bayard, Elizabeth Douglas. Episcopalian. Democrat.
Pursuits have ranged over three fields: writing (history, biography, criticism, current affairs, fiction, and satire), editing (numerous magazines), and government service (recurrent).
Began as founder (with Selden Rodman) of the widely publicized Yale undergraduate magazine, the Harkness Hoot. Published first book, Challenge to Defeat: Goethe's World and Spengler's Century, in 1932. Joined Vanity Fair as associate editor in the same year, also contributing stories and sketches; columnist on Washington Post, 1933-1934; editorial associate, Fortune, 1934-1936. After contributing also to Harper's, the Atlantic Monthly, Story in its prime, etc., turned freelance to write a novel, Hannibal Hooker (1938), an adventure yarn, A Yank in the RAF (1940) before interruption by war service. Returned from the latter to write The March of Freedom (1946), a layman's history of America. Served on the New Republic 1946-1947 as senior editor and occasional contributor, leaving it on political grounds. Joined The Reporter at its inception (1948) as senior writer, and after a four-year time-out first to write Horace Greeley, a biography (1950) and then to serve in the Department of the Army and the Foreign Service abroad. Rejoined The Reporter as contributing editor, again writing essays and articles. Switched to Horizon as managing editor at its inception (1958), writing fairly frequent satirical and other pieces for it besides, while also engaged on a historical series for American Heritage that resulted in a book on prominent American movers and shakers overseas, Innocence Abroad (1958).
Continued as editor of Horizon until 1963; editor of Horizon Books 1963-1967, senior writer 1967-1968. In this period produced two further books, The Horizon Book of Ancient Greece (1965) and The Horizon Book of Eating and Drinking Through the Ages (1968). Also delivered occasional lectures and wrote documentary television scripts.
Government service: Office of War Information 1941-1945, first in charge of German language broadcasts from New York, then of various psychological warfare operations conducted from London; second to SHAEF as chief of Radio Luxembourg (September 1944) and subsequently to United States Forces European Theater as policy advisor on information control matters in Germany. In 1948-1949, tours of duty with Department of the Army as Lt. Col., Military Intelligence. In 1950, civilian tour of duty for the same in Austria, followed by appointment as Foreign Service Reserve Officer and First Secretary at Vienna, first as head of U.S. information activities in that country under quadripartite occupation, then as director of all U.S. Public Affairs there, 1952-1953.
Home: Woods End Lane, Wesport, Connecticut.
Died: July, 1974.
Based on a curriculum vitae prepared by W. H. Hale, 1961 June.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Horizon; The New Republic; Reporter; Journalism; National socialism; Periodicals; Prisoners of War -- Germany; Propaganda, Anti-communist; World politics -- 1945-1989; World War, 1939-1945 -- Psychological aspects; Austria -- Foreign relations -- United States; Dachau (Germany: Concentration camp); Germany -- History -- 1933-1945; Germany -- History -- 1945-1955; United States -- Foreign relations -- Austria; Authors; Diplomats; Editors; Journalists; Ascoli, Max, 1898-1978; Bliven, Bruce, 1889-1977; Hale, William Harlan, 1910-1974; Neutra, Richard Joseph, 1892-1970; Villard, Oswald Garrison, 1872-1949; Yale University -- Students; Buchenwald (Concentration camp)
- CORRESPONDENCE, Series I
  - General
    - 1917-1949 (Box 1, Folder 1-31)
    - 1950-1971, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 32-59)
  - Select
    - Bingham, Alfred, 1932-1939, n. d. (Box 3, Folder 60-61)
    - Common Sense
      General
      See: box 3, folders 60-61 box 3, folders 68-71
    - Harkness Hoot, 1930-1931, undated (Box 3, Folder 62-64)
    - The Reporter, 1947-1949 (Box 3, Folder 65-67)
    - Rodman, Selden, 1930-1936, undated (Box 3, Folder 68-71)
    - Vienna correspondence, 1945-1954, undated (Box 3, Folder 72-81)
    - Wohlforth, Mildred, 1936-1939, undated (Box 3, Folder 82)
    - Family letters, 1924, 1945, undated (Box 3, Folder 83)
    - Photocopies of letters to W.H. Hale sold by W. H. Hale in 1971
      See also: William Bayard Hale Papers (MS 814)
      - Jeffers, Robinson, 1930 February 1 (Box 3, Folder 84)
      - Mencken, H. L., 1927 April 17 (Box 3, Folder 84)
      - Porter, Katherine Anne, 1932 July 8 (Box 3, Folder 84)
      - Wilder, Thornton, 1930 October 19 (Box 3, Folder 84)
      - Wright, Frank Loyd, 1930 November 12 (Box 3, Folder 84)
- WRITINGS, Series II
  - Published Books
    - Challenge to Defeat, 1932: contract, correspondence, 1931-1932 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Hannibal Hooker: His Death and Adventures, 1938: contract, correspondence, 1938 April 19, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - March of Freedom, 1946: royalty statement, reviews, 1947, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Horace Greeley: Voice of the People, 1950
      - Notes, [ca. 1948-1950] (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Correspondence, 1948-1950 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Innocence Abroad, 1957: draft, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Horizon Book of Ancient Greece, 1965: author's agreement, correspondence, 1969 May, July (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Unpublished Books
    - Americans Abroad
      - Chapter 1: outlines, drafts, notes, [ca. 1955] (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - Chapter 2: draft, [ca. 1955] (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - America's First Line of Forgotten Men Abroad: outline, [1955] (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - The Believers: TMS, 1934 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - The Blow That Ended Summer: TMS, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Ghosts of Berlin
      - Chapter 1, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
      - Chapter 2, undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
      - Chapter 3, undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
      - Chapter 4, undated (Box 5, Folder 16)
      - Chapter 5, undated (Box 5, Folder 17)
      - Chapter 6, undated (Box 5, Folder 18)
      - Chapter 7, undated (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Women in America
      - Correspondence, memoranda, 1967-1968 (Box 6, Folder 20)
      - Chapter 1: notes, research materials, drafts, undated (Box 6, Folder 21-24)
      - Chapter 2: notes, research materials, drafts, undated (Box 6, Folder 25-28)
      - Chapter 3: notes, research materials, drafts, undated (Box 7, Folder 29-32)
      - Chapter 4: notes, research materials, drafts, undated (Box 7, Folder 33-35)
      - Chapter 5: notes, research materials, undated (Box 7, Folder 36-37)
      - Chapter 5: drafts, undated (Box 8, Folder 38-39)
      - Chapter 6: notes, research materials, drafts, undated (Box 8, Folder 40-43)
      - Chapter 7: notes, research materials, drafts, undated (Box 8, Folder 44-47)
      - Chapter 8: drafts, undated (Box 9, Folder 48-49)
      - Chapter 9: notes, research materials, drafts, undated (Box 9, Folder 50-52)
      - Chapter 10: notes, research materials, drafts, undated (Box 9, Folder 53-55)
      - Bibliography, undated (Box 9, Folder 56)
  - Articles
    - 1919-1930 (Box 10, Folder 57-64)
    - [ca. 1930]-1934 (Box 11, Folder 65-71)
    - 1935-1953 (Box 12, Folder 72-83)
    - 1954-1970, undated (Box 13, Folder 84-91)
  - Radio Broadcasts
    - 1942 November - 1943 April (Box 13, Folder 92-93)
    - 1943 May - 1944 January (Box 14, Folder 94-100)
  - Television Broadcasts
    - 1959 February - December (Box 14, Folder 101)
  - Speeches
    - 1934, 1946, 1957 (Box 14, Folder 102)
  - Writings of Others
    - undated (Box 14, Folder 103)
- PERSONAL AND BIOGRAPHICAL PAPERS, Series III
  - Diary, 1951 December 28 - 1952 October 20 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Funeral orations, undated (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous notes, 1929, 1946, undated (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - School memorabilia, 1918-1931 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Yale College course notes, [1927-1931] (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Photographs, [ca. 1910-1966] (Box 15, Folder 6-7)
  - Passports and identification cards, 1938-1966 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Calling cards, undated (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Travel memorabilia, 1931-1966, undated (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Vienna invitations, 1950-1953, undated (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Printed memorabilia, 1926-1945, undated (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Partial catalogue of library of W. H. Hale, [ca. 1965] (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - Drawings, undated (Box 16, Folder 14)
  - Newspaper clippings, [ca. 1941-1953] (Box 16, Folder 15)
  - Biographical data, 1945-1967, undated (Box 16, Folder 16)
  - Books presented to W. H. Hale by Selden Rodman
    - Rodman, Selden. "Harold Cooper,", 1930 (Box 17, Folder 17)
    - Rodman, Selden. Mortal Triumph and Other Poems, 1932 (Box 17, Folder 18)
    - Rodman, Selden. Lawrence: The Last Crusade, 1937 (Box 17, Folder 19)
    - Rodman, Selden. The Airmen, 1941 (Box 17, Folder 20)
    - Rodman, Selden. Conversations With Artists, 1957 (Box 17, Folder 21)
    - Rodman, Belden, and Carole Cleaver. Horace Pippin: The Artist as Black American, 1972 (Box 17, Folder 22)
    - Rodman, Selden. Tongues of Fallen Angels, 1974 (Box 17, Folder 23)
- TOPICAL FILES, Series IV
  - American occupation of Germany - reports, 1945 August 1 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Anti-Nazi groups - reports: French Forces of the Interior, [1944] (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Concentration camps - reports
    - Buchenwald, 1945 April 24 (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Dachau, 1945 May 12 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - German anti-Nazis - reports on interrogations, 1945 April-August (Box 18, Folder 4)
    See also: box 18, folders 16-17
  - German army
    - Reports on interrogations, 1944 October-1945 July (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Reports on morale, 1944 May-1945 June (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - German cities - reports
    - Aachen, 1944 December 9 (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - Darmstadt, 1945 June 27 (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - Mainz, 1945 April 22 (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - Marburg, 1945 July 2 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - German civilians - reports
    - Attitude toward Allied occupation, 1945 July 19 (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - Attitude toward Allied radio broadcasts, 1945 June 5 (Box 18, Folder 9)
    - Exposure to Allied leaflets, 1945 June 28 (Box 18, Folder 10)
    - Interrogations, 1944 November-1945 July (Box 18, Folder 11)
    - Morale, 1944 May-Dec, undated (Box 18, Folder 12)
    - Reactions to Allied brochure on concentration camps, 1945 June (Box 18, Folder 13)
  - German politics, 1944 July-1945 August (Box 18, Folder 14)
  - German prisoners of war - reports
    General note
    See also: box 18, folder 4
    - Camps in the U. S., 1943 November 10 (Box 18, Folder 15)
    - Interrogations, 1944 June-1945 July (Box 18, Folder 16)
    - Interrogations: summary reports on attitudes, 1941 August-1945 June (Box 18, Folder 17)
    - Morale, 1944 June-November (Box 18, Folder 18)
    - Reactions to combat leaflets, 1944 June 15 (Box 18, Folder 19)
  - German trade unions - report: "Preparations for Trade Union Activities in Bavaria", 1945 August 8 (Box 18, Folder 20)
  - Mann, Thomas: "Germany and the Germans" (address), 1945 May 29 (Box 18, Folder 21)
  - Psychological warfare
    - Directives
      - Allied, 1943-1945 (Box 18, Folder 22)
      - British, 1944 (Box 18, Folder 23)
      - United States, 1944-1945 (Box 18, Folder 24)
    - Intelligence summaries, 1944-1945 (Box 18, Folder 25)
    - Interview reports with U. S. psychological warfare personnel, 1948, 1950 (Box 18, Folder 26)
  - Radio broadcasts - transcripts of short wave broadcasts for German and United States audiences, 1943 February 28-June 16 (Box 19, Folder 27)
  - Resistance movements - reports in German
    - Freiheitsaktion Bayern (F.A.B.), 1945 May (Box 19, Folder 28)
    - Organisation Sieben (0-7), 1945 May (Box 19, Folder 28)
  - United States government
    - Dept. of the Army. Civil Affairs Division. New York Field Office - study and reports: "Letters from Young Germans", 1948 (Box 19, Folder 29)
    - State Department - notes and memoranda, 1955-1956, undated (Box 19, Folder 30)
  - United States Information Agency, 1951-1955 (Box 19, Folder 31)
- PRINTED MATTER, Series V
  - Allied Expeditionary Force
    - Psychological Warfare Division
      - An Account of Its Operations in the Western European Campaign, 1944-1945, 1945 October (Box 19, Folder 1)
      - Current Combat Leaflets No. 30, 1944 November 1 (Box 19, Folder 2)
      - White Bombs, undated (Box 19, Folder 2)
      - European theater - leaflets (German language), [ca. 1944-1945] (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - Periodicals in German - Nachrichten für die Truppe, 1944 November 18-December 29, 1945 April 12 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Anti-Soviet propaganda
    - English language, [ca.1950-1953] (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - German language, [ca. 1950-1953] (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Catholic church and Hitler's attacks on it, undated (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - France
    - Periodicals
      - Inside France, 1940 June 8, 15 (Box 20, Folder 8)
      - Le Soir, 1943 November 9 (Box 20, Folder 8)
      - Propaganda against U.S., [post-1945] (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - Germany
    - East zone, [post-1945] (Box 20, Folder 10)
    - National-Komitee freies Deutschland. Bezirk Leipzig, [1945] (Box 20, Folder 11)
    - Nazi publications
      - Deutschlands Erwachen, [1924?] (Box 20, Folder 12)
      - Miscellaneous, 1937-1943, undated (Box 20, Folder 13-15)
    - Periodicals
      - Der Adler, 1943 October 5 (Box 20, Folder 16)
      - Die Oase, 1943 March 21 (Box 20, Folder 16)
        See: Oversize Materials
      - Die Wehrmacht, 1943 September 1, 15 (Box 20, Folder 16)
      - Die Woche, 1943 September 20 (Box 20, Folder 16)
    - Propaganda
      - French language, 1923 (Box 20, Folder 17)
      - Military - English and French languages, undated (Box 20, Folder 18)
      - For U.S.
        - Facts in Review, 1940 July 22-1941 May 26 (Box 20, Folder 19)
        - German News Agency and the News, [1940] (Box 20, Folder 19)
  - Great Britain
    - Germany. Basic Handbook. Pt. III: Nazi Occupied Europe, 1944 (Box 20, Folder 20)
    - Government publications, 1941-1945 (Box 20, Folder 21)
    - Government publications: war histories, 1940-1945 (Box 21, Folder 22-24)
  - Hungary
    - Government publications, 1952 (Box 21, Folder 25)
    - Publications re: events of 1956 (Box 21, Folder 26)
  - Luxembourg: The Luxembourg Grey Book, [1942] (Box 21, Folder 27)
  - Prisoners of war: periodicals
    - Ausblick, 1945 March (Box 21, Folder 28)
    - Der Ruf, 1945 Mar, April (Box 21, Folder 28)
  - Russia: propaganda for Austria, [post-1945] (Box 21, Folder 29)
  - U.S. government publications
    - English language for overseas distribution, 1942-1943, undated (Box 21, Folder 30)
    - French language, undated (Box 21, Folder 31)
    - German language, 1945-1953 (Box 21, Folder 32-33)
    - German language, 1952-1953, undated (Box 22, Folder 34-35)
    - Nuremberg trials, 1951 (Box 22, Folder 36)
    - Periodicals
      - Amerika (Russian language), undated (Box 22, Folder 36)
      - U.S.A., undated (Box 22, Folder 37)
      - Victory, undated (Box 22, Folder 37)
      - Yank, 1945 September 9 (Box 22, Folder 37)
    - Propaganda
      - French language, 1942-1943, undated (Box 22, Folder 38)
      - For German civilians, 1943-1944 (Box 22, Folder 39)
    - War histories
      - European theater, 1945 (Box 22, Folder 40)
      - France, 1945 (Box 22, Folder 41)
      - Invasion of Europe, 1945 (Box 22, Folder 42)
      - North Africa, 1943 (Box 22, Folder 43)
      - Pacific theater, 1945-1946 (Box 22, Folder 44-45)
  - U.S. Military Government - Germany: Proclamation No. 1, [1944] (Box 22, Folder 44-45)
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  - Amerika (Russian language), undated (Box 23, Folder 44-45)
  - Die Oase, 1943 March 21 (Box 23, Folder 44-45)
  - Die Wehrmacht, 1943 September 1, 15 (Box 23, Folder 44-45)
  - U.S. Military Government: Proclamation No. 1, [1944] (Box 23, Folder 44-45)